OK.
And the meeting has started.
For recording purposes,
I am now letting everybody in from the
lobby.
Good morning, everybody.
As usual,
it does take a minute or two for everyone
to come in from the lobby.
And so in the meanwhile,
my name is Dominic Serlo and I'm with the
Department of Health and we are here as
the Department of Health to help support
this meeting.
This is the meeting of the Patient
Qualification and Safety Committee with
Ian Dunn as the chair.
And just as a reminder,
we are recording this meeting.
So Please remember to keep language in
the background to appropriate language so
that we can ensure we can post this video
at a later date.
That is also one of two reasons why we do
not have video for everyone.
And I'll, once I finish speaking,
I will actually be turning my video off
is we want to ensure that everybody has
enough broadband is the second reason,
or I'm sorry, not broadband,
but bandwidth to be able to remain in the
meeting as much as possible.
And what we've discovered,
of course is that because some areas of
the state do not have as good as Internet
as some other areas,
we want to always make sure that people
are able to remain in the meeting as much
as possible.
And while sometimes they still end up
dropping off due to that lack of Internet
or poor Internet quality,
we want to try to reduce that as much as
possible.
And so with that,
I will turn it on over to Ian.
Ian and I will get that document posted
in the chat for the clinical support
framework.
Perfect.
Thank you guys so much for coming today.
We are in the patient qualification and
Safety committee.
Welcome.
We will be going over a medication
interactions.
So I am happy to see a couple people from
the prior meetings that can help out with
that.
And if we wanna go ahead and begin,
if you would like to raise your hand and
introduce yourself,
your area of expertise and what he brings
you to the patient qualification and
Safety committee, that would be great.
Good morning, Doctor Viva.
I've unmuted your microphone.
Whenever you're ready,
go ahead and unmute yourself.
Thank you so much.
Good morning everyone.
I'm Doctor Lita Fatemi.
I am an internal medicine physician.
I was at UNM for a decade as an academic
hospitalist.
Now I'm in Hospice and of life work with
our patients in the community and we also
have our conscious physicians
psychedelics Academy.
And again, you know,
these topics of the committee are just
wonderful because as we're teaching our
Academy students who are healthcare
professionals, you know,
this is one of the biggest topics we talk
about is patient qualification,
contraindication medications.
Glad to be here.
Thank you so much for creating this
platform.
Thank you.
Next up is Al Alan,
I've enabled your microphone.
You may unmute yourself whenever you're
ready.
Thank you.
Good morning everyone.
Happy to be here.
My name is Ellen Shimmels.
I'm a psychiatric minor health nurse
practitioner in Albuquerque.
I'm also an Army veteran and a clinical
professor at Emory University.
I've been a psychiatric nurse now for
about 30 years,
about 20 years as a nurse practitioner.
I have advanced training in many
different trauma focused psychotherapies,
extensive experience in clinical
education with a focus on trauma informed,
evidence based and ethically grounded
care.
Happy to be here and support and bring my
knowledge to the group.
Thank you.
Thank you, Alan.
And just a friendly reminder at this
point, if anyone else would like to speak,
please go ahead and raise your hand on
the teams.
That way I can go ahead and enable your
microphone credentials.
Since no one else is requesting to speak
at this time, I'll pass it back to you.
Ian, ready for Hey,
so we will begin discussion on medication
interactions if you could pull up the
document for me.
So this is a place list of basic
medication interactions that I've found.
So if there is any, you know,
ones that are missing, I am not perfect,
we can definitely add those.
So you are gonna see some familiar ones.
Ones we've already talked about are
lithium, Maois and stimulant use.
This also goes a little bit broader into
ones that aren't going to be blocked from
participation,
but are going to could dampen the
psychedelic effects.
And so I know in the dosage committee
they were talking about or they adopted
other dosages.
So like maybe someone on these
medications could need a substantially
higher dose.
And then there's also other drugs that
increase the the seizure threshold and
that potentiate serotonergic effects.
So there's a couple in here.
We'll go ahead and start with the first
one that we haven't already adopted,
which is going to be atypical
antipsychotics.
So current main concern with psilocybin,
they're likely to block psychedelic
effects through 5 HT 2A receptor
antagonism Tier 2.
We want to get them extra clinical
support, you know, risk mitigation plan,
maybe get them that other dose or higher
dose if they were not going to taper off,
but should definitely be recognized as
something that needs extra consideration.
Is there any comments or discussion on
atypical antipsychotics?
All right, seeing none,
we can go ahead and go on to SSRIs S
slash Snris.
Their best supported issue is blunted
subjective and possible therapeutic
effect.
So they as well may require a higher dose.
Again, medication review,
see if they need extra safety
implementation if they are going to get a
higher dose.
Not necessarily restricted,
just kind of a warning.
Anyone have any questions, comments,
concerns, or discussion on SSRIs or Snris?
All right,
now we'll move to tricyclic
antidepressants.
So it's just again,
a possible serotonergic caution.
Interaction risk is limited, but you know,
the provider should still know and a
safety plan should be in place.
It should be Tier 2, not very restricted,
but again, just there as extra precaution.
Any questions, comments, concerns,
or discussion on tricyclic
antidepressants?
Seeing none,
we'll go on to other serotonergic
antidepressants.
These are going to be Trazodone,
velazodone,
bortaroxetine and other serotonergic
antidepressants.
They have a possible attenuation of
psychedelic effects and serotonergic
interaction concerns.
These aren't very well established.
So again, it's just a clinical warning,
not anything restrictive.
Any questions, comments,
concerns on other serotonergic
antidepressants?
Cool.
And then we next we have bupropion.
It is not primarily serotonergic.
There's less evidence for blunting,
but it can lower the seizure threshold.
So caution is reasonable.
Again,
Tier 2 is just having them make a safety
plan and make sure that they are all that
we take extra time to review what is
going on with their medications.
So Tier 2,
I will again open for discussion
questions, comments, concerns.
Allen.
Allen, I've enabled your microphone.
Go ahead.
I'm sorry I wasn't quick enough on the
jump.
I put it in the chat,
but so I guess with the Trazodone list,
I would probably include Mirtazapine and
even Buspirone.
They're not even for as far as they're
tenergic agents that we should be maybe
aware of on that Tier 2.
I don't know if you were trying to lift,
I know you're saying others,
but I mean they're probably more they're
more common than Velazodone or
vortioxetine.
So Mirtazapine and thanks.
Thank you, Alan.
James, I've enabled your microphone.
You're able to unmute yourself whenever
you're ready.
Morning everyone and Ian,
thanks again for chairing this committee.
You know, going back to that,
I do agree with the mirtazapine on the
Wellbutrin or bupropion there.
There's a mixed bag on that with the
evidence that shows because of that up
regulation receptor that it actually does
a different mechanism.
It's considered ADNR.
And so with the DNR's,
they're necessarily used maybe not an
interaction.
So I don't know if it needs to go there.
That's just my thought on, you know,
the pharmacy side of it.
Again, I,
I think the mirtazapine's a great
addition.
I just think we just more discussion on
the bupropion.
I think we need.
Thank you.
Yeah,
and I definitely don't see bupropion as a
like serotonergic issue,
but I definitely the only reason it was
really included as a warning is because
it can lower seizure threshold.
So caution would be reasonable,
but I would definitely be open to more
discussion on bupropion.
Alan, whenever you're ready,
go ahead and unmute yourself, please.
Thanks again.
Yeah, I, I,
I also wanted to stay away from saying
anything about serotonin with the
bupropion because it's,
and it's not a serotonergic agent when we
say lowers and see their seizures
threshold like that.
I, I can't remember where,
where seizures are anyway,
because one of the big things,
the highest concern is like eating
disorders,
any kind of alcohol use with seizures and
history of seizures, of course.
So I feel like we're maybe addressing
that already with where we put seizures
in general on the other list outside the
medication list, if that makes sense.
So then we wouldn't be concerned about
the bupropion,
would be concerned about the potential
for seizures if someone has a history of
seizures or if they have, you know,
the alcohol or potential withdrawal or
they have eating disorders.
I guess it's like a chicken and the egg
thing.
But yeah, I would just take the serotonin,
which you did out of there.
Thanks.
All right,
so I've updated the bupropion to just say
can lower seizure threshold.
So caution is reasonable.
Is that what we're thinking,
or would you all prefer to just rather
strike it completely?
Alan, go right ahead.
Your microphone is enabled.
Sorry.
I, I think with, again,
if we could answer the question about
what we are saying about anyone with a
history of seizures and those types of
things.
Because otherwise I don't think you can
blanketly say that without someone having
a, you know, the history.
And if you look at a history of like
seizure disorders or active eating
disorders,
that could potentially lower that seizure
threshold,
which you're more concerned about.
I guess that might be,
that would already maybe negate someone
from being, you know, from,
from being able to participate in the 1st
place if it's active.
You see what I'm saying?
So it won't necessarily matter about the
propion.
And I just worry that if keeping the list,
keeping bupropion would be like a maybe a
secondary level of defense, you know,
but I I just don't want it to, you know,
to be, you know, I don't,
I guess I'll worry about someone with,
you know,
thinking that maybe bupropion is one of
the safer agents because it doesn't have
that serotonergic pathway would be a
reason to maybe.
Yeah, get it off the list.
OK.
You already did that.
Sorry.
No, you're good.
You're good.
I completely agree with what you're
saying.
And we already do have a history of
seizure disorders under extra caution.
So you're right if that is our primary
concern and the evidence is not as strong
as with lithium.
So I'm pretty OK with dismissing
bupropion.
So next we had benzodiazepines,
they just dampen the AQ experience and
maybe reduce therapeutic utility.
They are also are kind of used to as a
reversal agent.
So chronic use of benzodiazepines may
require an additional dose or other
mechanisms.
So I did say clinical support.
Let's get a, a figure out what they need.
Maybe they need a higher dosage,
maybe they need to taper off whatever
their provider decides,
but if they are on them at the time of
administration,
we do need to take that into
consideration.
How do y'all feel about that?
Cool.
And then cannabis has the potential to
potentiate serotoninergic effects.
Again, not that it's dangerous,
just that hey,
let's take another look at it make sure
that we're doing everything we can for
these patients again, not a restriction,
just let's pay attention all right and
then are there any Medicare Oops,
sorry Ellen, I'm so sorry Ellen,
go ahead whenever you're ready.
No, so I mean like I you know,
obviously cannabis is also considered a
medical.
I just,
I just wonder if we should consider,
and I guess alcohol's already on our
other list.
I just kind of think about cannabis and
alcohol,
even though it's obviously not in the
same class.
But I mean, you know,
I kind of think about that.
Do we want to mention alcohol or anything
like that here or just keep with the
cannabis because of the medical
indications?
I only chose cannabis because of the fact
that they're both serotonergic.
But in theory,
we could do alcohol as well.
It may also dampen the acute experience
and may reduce therapeutic utility.
It has a lot of mechanism of action
similarities with benzos.
So we could add alcohol.
Is that a common?
Yeah.
I mean, that's what I was thinking.
But if again,
I just off the top my head can't remember.
I mean,
obviously acute intoxication would be on
our, I was already on our list,
but I don't remember where else alcohol
fell on the on the other side of the list.
Not that, you know,
when we were talking about the like
history of use, right,
with the history and stuff.
Yeah.
So, so it might already be covered.
I don't want it to be redundant.
Thanks.
Yeah, so definitely will consider alcohol.
Does anyone have any other medications or
medication classes that I've missed?
Anne, Anne,
your microphone is enabled whenever
you're ready.
Go ahead and unmute yourself, please.
Just in my work in Colorado,
I've noticed that people on GLP ones have
had delayed onset.
So potentially something to mention in
there.
Thank you, Anne.
Alan,
I went ahead and enabled your microphone.
Go ahead.
I just want,
I know we have lithium listed
specifically,
but I don't know if we should also
consider lamotrigine and other mood
stabilizer as that Tier 2 just because of
the same thing.
Like it's kind of known to blunt the
blunt psychedelic effects as well.
Thank you, Alan James,
I've enabled your microphone.
Go ahead and I'll meet yourself whenever
you're ready.
Thank you again.
You know, just going back to that GLP one,
I think that's something to talk about
and discuss,
and it's something that in the literature,
it's coming very prevalent.
This is something that we do need to kind
of think about as a group.
I think GLP once needs to be somewhere in
here as a precautionary thing and or just
a like an FYI if you're on these because
there's so many people on them currently
and increasing in what we say numbers on
concentration there,
but a lot of more people come in.
So thank you.
Thank you, James.
Dr.
Lida, I've enabled your microphone.
Go ahead and unmute yourself whenever
you're ready.
Yeah, you know,
to resonate with that GLP ones I've heard
in the community where people are even
just micro dosing, you know,
for four days in a row and they'll they
don't feel much.
And then on,
on the 4th day when they're taking their
GLP one at a higher dose and a micro dose
at a higher dose, then four hours later,
they have a huge macro dose experience.
So it's because of that lower GI motility
that GLP ones create.
I totally agree that that has to be
considered.
And maybe for two weeks people shouldn't
be really taking it before journey.
The other medication group that I would
be also advising you know to to look at
is hormone replacement therapy,
especially in females,
perimenopause or menopausal females who
are utilizing estrogen that can enhance
the effects because of serotonergic
effects as well.
But we have other experts here on the in
the committee that can speak to that as
well.
Thank you Doctor Lita, back to you.
Perfect.
So I've added GLP one's the main concern
that I've heard is the potential to delay
onset.
Is that the am I getting that right or
are we is there and more that I should
say because I feel like the risk is more
so that like because the onset is so
delayed maybe potential to significantly.
OK.
And then?
We the other one that we hadn't discussed
as fully was the mood stabilizers.
So how do we feel about lamotrigine and
other mood stabilizers for psilocybin use?
Doctor Lida, your microphone is enabled.
You may begin when you're ready.
Doctor Lita, if you can hear us,
we cannot hear you.
Your microphone is enabled.
So sorry, Doctor Lita,
we still cannot hear you.
If you're able to put it in the chat,
that'll be applicable as well.
And thank you, Dominic.
OK, she put in the chat.
Sorry, my phone isn't working.
Understandable.
If you're able to put it in the chat,
please do so.
Just a friendly reminder,
as Dominic posted,
the microphone button is what's utilized
in the Teams app to mute or unmute
yourself or *6 from a telephone.
That's voice only, Ian.
No one else has their hand up.
So I'm going to send it back to you.
Allen, Ian, you're Ian, you're muted.
I'm so sorry.
And Allen, your microphone's enabled.
Go ahead and begin whenever you're ready.
Now you're muting him.
I, I don't know.
I mean, I,
I didn't necessarily mean to put mood
stabilizers as a whole class because
lamotrigine is the only one I've seen in
literature that's actually linked to kind
of muting that effect.
I haven't there should be no reason for
valproic acid to do that,
primarily because lamotrigine works on
the glutamate system.
But again, I, I, I mean,
if we want to put it as a class,
but put it Lamotrigine as an example or
something like that.
But if we're doing like individual meds,
I would probably lean on the side of just
leaving the Lamotrigine there as a Tier 2.
Thanks.
Perfect.
So I went ahead and put Lamotrigine since
that is the one she specifically listed
as well as you right now.
So they're likely to block psychedelic
effect in Tier 2.
And then are there any other medications
that we still feel are missing?
All righty.
So why don't we go ahead and vote on the
adoption of if I'm going to give a little
bit more time, Are you all sure?
Any other medications we should consider?
OK,
we will go ahead and vote on the adoption
of this medication tier placement.
All those in favor,
please raise your hand.
And I believe there's there is one Doctor
Lee that has a comment in the chat if you
want to look at that before the vote.
Yes,
let's see in regards the concern is
potentially dosing over the necessary
effective dose and then having a major
trip that was not expected likely?
OK.
So I've gone ahead and updated it to GLP
one's potential for significantly delayed
onset.
If additional dosing is provided due to
the delay,
the potential for overdosing is
substantial.
Ellen.
Sorry, I was just saying it.
Yeah,
I was just saying it in the chat too.
Is maybe like like we have likely for
some of these and potential for some of
these.
Why don't we just use the same verbiage
instead of using likely?
I mean,
I don't I'm I just think that maybe
that's a stronger word for not
necessarily a good reason.
Thanks.
So I always used potential for what we
have more less documented information.
So like atypical antipsychotics,
we have very extensive documentation that
they block the five HT 2A receptor which
we believe is responsible for the
psychedelic more at least partially
responsible for the psychedelic
experience.
So because of that it is very likely
unless you are like everyone processes
different medicine differently.
So if you are the odd one out,
maybe it doesn't for you.
Whereas potential is we know the
relationship between these,
but we don't have as much evidence,
if that makes sense.
Oh, sure.
Then I guess for lamotrigine,
I would say may instead of likely.
And that's I guess for the antipsychotics.
I understand likely is maybe a better
verb for that,
but just kind of I was just trying to be
mindful of the words.
Thanks.
I appreciate the explanation.
That makes sense.
Yeah.
So I changed lamotrigine to May.
GLP ones are still potential to
significantly delay onset if additional
dosing is provided.
Due to the due to the delay,
the potential for overdosing is
substantial.
But then if I could ask when we say best
supported issue is blunted subjective and
possibly therapeutic effect under
SSRISNRIS,
maybe there would be a way to make that a
little clearer because that so I could
say it's blunted psychedelic effects.
So what most people report is that it
almost it required a much higher dose to
get the same results.
Right, right.
And and I appreciate that.
But I guess the the best supported issue.
I don't understand that verbiage,
like why?
Let's maybe be consistent with what we're
saying.
So likely to say likely blunted
psychedelic effect or something,
because the best supported issue is just
not how we worded anything else.
That's thank you.
Likely blunted psychedelic effects
Potential serotonergic caution and
reaction risk is limited.
Potential unpotentialist in July onset.
OK, I think this is good.
May blunt.
Yeah.
OK, psychedelic effects.
How about May potentiate?
All right,
any other comments either in the chat or
out loud?
All right, seeing no comments,
we can now move on to the medication
interaction adoption.
So at this time,
if you are in support of adopting the
current medication interactions as stand,
please raise your hand.
I did 6:00 AM.
See you all right.
You may put your hands down and if you
are against the adoption of the current
medication interactions as they stand,
please raise your hand.
I do not see any.
So with six yes and 0 no's the motion is
adopted,
which means we can get to our larger
package.
Because the work of this committee is
almost done,
we will go ahead and consolidate the
recommendations into one document,
which I should have as soon as SharePoint
wants to load.
All right, Jorge,
the consolidated recommendations have
been moved into the meeting folder.
If you can just go ahead and open them
for me.
Is that in today's folder for the 17th?
Yes, Meetings.
Meetings.
Found it.
OK.
You see that that yes.
So these are the consolidated
recommendations of everything that we
have gone through so far as a committee.
So if you want to Scroll down to the
initial qualifying conditions table,
we're just going to review everything
this committee has done and make sure we
have not missed anything.
So treatment resistant depression,
post traumatic stress disorder,
substance use disorders and end of life
distress are the four initial legislative
qualifying conditions assigned to the ICD
10 codes on the right.
And Metz has a comment.
I'm so sorry about that, Ed, Go ahead.
No worries.
It may be a little late to mention this,
but after reviewing the original Hopkins
studies on end of life distress,
technically those people qualified for
those studies because they had
generalized anxiety disorder.
And I'm just wondering about the
alignment between, you know,
our desire to have Medicaid cover these
treatments and having AZ code as the I
CD10.
I wonder if it would be more useful to
have generalized anxiety disorder as the
ICD 10 code, I don't know,
in addition to or in lieu of the Z code.
Yeah.
And then actually, Dominic, Yeah, Thanks,
Ann.
That's a really great point.
And just to let you know,
the ICD 10 codes here are not necessarily
what will be utilized with regard to
billing.
We actually are meeting with HCA.
Actually I have to look at my calendar,
but here coming up soon just to to go
over what potential billing codes are.
So if the main concern on that is
regarding billing,
don't worry about that because we're
going to be looking that over with HCA to
sort of see, you know,
what codes would be appropriate.
And so we'll actually bring that to
either this committee or as we just move
forward, if we have permission,
we'll just sort of adjust those codes to
match what would work with HCA for the
billing.
Yeah,
these codes are largely for the research
and continuous improvement committee who
are documenting, you know,
the effectiveness of these treatments and
ensuring that we are doing things
properly and we're getting as much data
as we can to make sure we're making a
safe program.
So it's more internal.
Just saying here's what they roughly line
up with so that we can track and ensure
the program,
but it doesn't have to do with billing.
Ellen, Ellen, go right ahead.
Thanks.
On a similar range for post traumatic
stress disorder.
I was just curious if we could use like
the F43-1,
like an X because 1-2 implies that it's a
chronic post traumatic stress disorder.
And there's no, I,
I haven't read that there's any specific
legislative condition that makes you have
to have chronic PTSD versus an acute PTSD.
And I might even err on the side of if
someone doesn't quite have meet all the
criteria that they might even have an
adjustment disorder.
I don't know if that's or,
or if we don't want to make that
distinguish, you know, distinguish nation,
that's fine.
But I just at least would put an F43 dash
or .
1 X because that implies all of the PTSD
diagnosis.
OK, perfect.
And then Dr.
Fatima, all right ahead.
Yeah, thank you.
I was thinking, Dominic,
if you guys wanna also when you talk to
the ACA about prolonged service codes,
it may be very appropriate to do so
because often these conversations go over
the allotted unexpected time.
And these codes are cover that face to
FaceTime and their utilization would be
really beneficial for the practice that
is, you know, looking to sign up for,
for this program.
So just something to look into with them,
maybe talk to them about the prolonged
service codes.
Thank you.
Thank you, Doctor Lita,
before I go ahead and enable your
microphone,
Lisa just to catch up in the chat and
commented that adjustment disorder would
be so helpful to have and Alan concurs
with that statement.
And Lisa,
your microphone is enabled whenever
you're ready.
Go right ahead.
Thank you.
I was wondering if you guys would
consider adding conditions like OCDADHD
and eating disorder to the least so these
aren't just the like for internal
translation of the legislative conditions
to ICD 10 codes.
At the moment,
we are going to implement the program
with these four conditions,
ensure that these four have access before
we create a huge patient demand that's
going to cripple the new industry because
there won't be enough centers and growers
and manufacturers to support them.
So let's ensure that they have time to
build up before we go ahead and endorse a
bunch of new conditions.
And then we have hundreds of thousands of
patients who can't get care at all.
Ellen, go ahead.
Ellen.
Thanks.
Yes, and I appreciate that.
I think we were just to have it on the
record,
the adjustment disorder comment was
really maybe not, you know,
meeting probably criteria for PTSD,
but maybe not quite.
And I think adjustment disorder could
collectively be used instead of AZ code
for end of life related to stress.
Or even when you're looking at someone
just being diagnosed with a medical
illness that they would potentially die
from,
I guess is part of that not not always
knowing that the end of life is imminent,
if that makes sense.
I think that there's some, you know,
I don't even know,
I know that they looked at GAD as was
mentioned earlier,
but I think that that would be really too
stringent.
But adjustment disorder kind of opens it
up in a way that there's something going
on that there's a there's a significant
adjustment too.
And that's, I don't know if that I mean,
because that's where I think what,
what is being said that could,
would still fall under these buckets,
but leave a little more,
maybe a little more laxity for,
for what it exactly is going on from the
patient side things.
So we're thinking F432 for end of life
distress.
Please correct me if I'm wrong.
I mean, that's, that's what I think.
But I, I would, I would also,
I just think that that's a,
a maybe a better,
a more collective way to capture that end
of life distress in whatever context
we're talking about.
I think I agree because I don't think end
of life distress only happens when you're
on palliative care.
I think people can have that kind of
distress even if let's say they had
cancer, thought they were going to die,
end up getting, you know,
their leg amputated and they're still
adjusting,
but they still had that fear of end of
life and that still causes a bunch of
existential distress.
So I could agree with adjustment disorder
even outside of necessarily palliative
care.
But I do think that the majority should
be what the legislators intended,
which would be Hospice and end of life
care.
If I don't, if actually,
if you just take the X off of the,
I think that that will cover the PTSD.
Now I think about it too,
because I didn't want to.
I'm used to seeing the XS when we're
implying like any of them,
but just to take it off,
to make it cleaner.
Thanks.
And you just did appreciate it.
Thank you, Alan.
Kate,
I've enabled your microphone whenever
you're ready.
Go ahead and unmute yourself, please.
Good morning, everybody.
Yeah, this is Kate Hawk.
And I'm closely involved with the end of
life care committee.
Yeah,
there there is this question about well,
where do we start and how broad can this
apply?
And in in the meeting,
Senator Steinborn actually confirmed that
they left end of life care,
our end of life open to be flexible.
So right now I think, you know,
this would be good to consider in our end
of life care committee, but you know,
there wasn't anything that said,
well this has to be Hospice or this has
to be palliative care.
So just wanted to mention that so maybe
we can look at this further as we go.
Yeah, so I've already updated it to F 43.
2,
which would be the adjustment disorder
codes.
So I think that that helps to really and
vision the end of life related distress
because I don't think it,
it only comes from like being in Hospice.
I think it can also come from just
hearing that you have a serious diagnosis
and you know,
if you're ever in the room with someone
during that, it is a certain type of,
of grief and, and end of life distress.
And so I definitely would agree with that.
I don't think they have to be in Hospice
care already.
I think they definitely can get it to
help them be more comfortable in those
census.
So does anyone.
So is F 43.2 OK with people?
I was just wondering about the one that
you removed.
Would it, you know,
would it work to have both?
Yeah, the palliative care Z code, Yeah,
I don't think we should remove that one.
That one applies to.
All right.
And Ellen, go ahead, Ellen, and thank you.
I agree that we should keep the Z code
there.
But then I would also say let's look at
the middle column and maybe take that
palliative care status off.
We can just say, you know,
just associated with or symptoms
associated with serious or life limiting
illness.
I think that that would cover it well
without just putting that palliative care
label on, I think.
Thank you, Allen.
And then just to catch up in the chat,
Lori asked,
does it have to be specific to end of
life illness or could it just be older
age and and cognitive?
That's fantastic, wonderful adjustment.
Thanks everyone for having such great
ideas.
Thank you.
Thank you all.
So I have changed it to end of life
distress with serious or life limiting
illness and then kept the Z code Z 51.5.
Added the adjustment disordered Z code F
43.2.
Is everyone any other comments?
No, OK.
We can go ahead and move on to the
clinical support framework.
This is what we have been putting those
medications into all day.
Tier 1, proceed with standard protocol.
Patient or provider may request
additional clinical support,
but it's patients without any Tier 2-3 or
Tier 4 criteria,
patients meeting criteria in this tier.
For Tier 2,
it's enhanced clinical support.
They remain eligible for participation,
but they need appropriate clinical
consideration,
which may include stabilization where
appropriate,
and thoughtful support planning.
The specific approach should be guided by
practitioner judgment and the
individual's patient individual patients
clinical contacts.
For Tier 2,
required documentation is a risk
mitigation plan to be available to the
facilitator slash administrator of
psilocybin,
A comprehensive medication review,
and a documented monitoring plan.
Tier 3 is specialist supported care.
Patients meeting criteria in this tier
may participate only with the required
Tier 2 documentation and documented
consultation and concurrence of two
practitioner signatories prior to
administration,
the primary psilocybin practitioner
responsible for the patient's care,
and a licensed specialist practicing
within their scope of licensure and
possessing expertise relevant to the
identified condition.
So this could be a psychiatrist,
a psychiatric mental health nurse
practitioner, A cardiologist,
A neurologist,
or other appropriately credentialed
clinician,
and then Tier 4 is not appropriate for
participation at this time.
Any questions, comments,
concerns on the actual framework?
Cool.
So now these are the clinical support
framework criteria.
So what is actually in each of these?
So active eating disorder or significant
malnutrition taking more than or equal to
a high intensity dose as defined by the
dosage administration and clinical
Practices committee.
So they designed that as being equal to
above 50 milligrams of psilocybin.
This would only usually be for patients,
you know,
that are taking medication that may blunt
their subjective effect and what they
perceive and get out of psilocybin
therapy.
That's why it's here.
Tier 3 specialist supported care,
history of bipolar 2 disorders,
history of delusional disorders,
history of dissociative disorders and
then Tier 4 not appropriate at this time.
So there's a couple situations.
If the individual is under the age of 18,
if they are pregnant,
if they are breastfeeding,
unless the patient and provider implement
A and document a plan to pump and discard
breast milk for at least 24 hours
following administration,
there are a couple of stabilization
before treatment conditions.
These mean we will accept them,
but we do need them to destabilize before
they are appropriate.
So this would be an active psychotic
episode, a history of Tias or Cvas,
clinically significant uncontrolled
hypertension,
uncontrolled diabetes mellitus,
uncontrolled seizure disorder,
current suicidal or homicidal ideation
with intent,
planner inability to maintain safety.
And then there are a couple of conditions
that are contraindications to
participation in psilocybin services.
Those are going to be a history of
schizophrenia spectrum disorders,
a history of persistent or current
psychotic disorder including psychosis
precipitated by serotonergic psychedelic
exposure, history of bipolar one disorder,
history of borderline personality
disorder, severe congestive heart failure,
known allergy to psilocybin containing
mushrooms,
and an active inability to provide
informed consent.
Everyone good with the criteria or do you
have any discussion on those?
Doctor Lita, your microphone is enabled.
Go ahead.
Thank you.
I would add coronary artery disease or
just atherosclerotic,
just a heart disease in general.
So just severe heart failure.
It does not, you know,
it does not cover all the cardiac
disorders.
And given that there's so many, there's a,
there's a really large number of
serotonin receptors in the heart muscle
itself that people can go into a cardiac
complication and even have a heart attack
during a session with psilocybin.
So I think that has to be a
contraindication cardiovascular disease.
Thank you, Doctor Lita, will you speak?
Yeah.
Education.
Thank you.
Thank you, Doctor.
Lita and Lori commented.
Or excuse me?
Yeah, Lori commented in the chat.
Why is borderline excluded?
I feel it would help my patients with
borderline.
No,
there is not substantial evidence that it
is helpful to borderline personality
disorder and there's some evidence that
it may exacerbate mood swings and
emotional instability as well as
splitting.
So it typically is not used for
borderline personality disorder.
There is some emerging evidence about the
use in bipolar 2 disorder,
but I have not seen any on bipolar,
I mean, borderline personality disorder.
All right.
So just to clarify,
we're adding coronary artery disease and
cardiovascular disease.
Anyone have any objections to that?
OK.
Any other conditions you think we need to
add?
And just in the chat game, Lori commented,
just because it's not shown to be helpful
does not necessary, does not necessitate,
excuse me, exclusion.
No, it doesn't.
But when it has been shown to cause harm
that that does,
it is a very high risk tool to give
someone with BPD because it can cause
mood instability and we don't want to be
the ones responsible for causing that.
But I do want to say this is not,
how do I say like it's not the end all be
all.
As soon as more research comes out which
the medical psilocybin program is
investing in,
we will be able to see more information.
And once we get more information and
maybe I'm completely off base and it
turns out that borderline personality
disorder is extremely helped by
psilocybin.
If that turns out to be the case,
then we will adjust going forward and we
would just strike it and add it as a
qualifying condition if it is helpful.
It's not the end all be all.
I just wanted to remind you all of that.
And then the medication interaction
considerations that we talked about
earlier copied and pasted into this.
So it is the exact same thing we talked
about and that is it.
So this is what's up for adoption is our
consolidated recommendations with the
additions that we have discussed.
All those in favor,
please raise your hand.
I do see six hands 7 perfect and you may
put your hands down,
although let me wait a little bit longer
for those to.
All right, all those opposed,
I do not see any.
All right,
so the consolidated recommendations are
adopted and that is what I had planned
for y'all today.
Does anyone else have any discussion or
things that you would like to discuss or?
Without anything,
I guess we can go ahead and set the next
meeting.
So hold on, let my calendar allow.
How does April 6th sound for everyone?
Perfect.
What time?
What?
What time are you in?
Nine AMI think that looks good on our end,
Johnny?
Yes.
Is that correct?
Yeah, Looks, looks good.
I think Dominic will be out of the office,
but otherwise I think that's good.
Yes, Johnny is correct.
But the meetings can continue even though
I'll be out.
You all have this done.
You're all doing this so very well.
And so I am not necessary for the process,
but I will review the video, of course,
afterwards.
Well, thank you all for being here.
I hope you have a wonderful rest of your
day.
Be safe out there.
And I appreciate all of your input and
for everyone taking the time to be here.
I love the conversations and thank you
for supporting this program.
Thank you, everyone.
Thank you, Ian.
Thank you, everybody.
Have a great and wonderful week.